The following content is provided
提供以下内容
under a Creative Commons license.
根据知识共享许可。
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare continue
您的支持将帮助MIT OpenCourseWare继续
to offer high quality educational resources for free.
免费提供高质量的教育资源。
To make a donation, or view additional materials
捐款或查看其他材料
from hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare
从数百门麻省理工学院的课程中，访问MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
在ocw.mit.edu。
PROFESSOR: Good morning, everyone.
教授：大家早上好。
Let's get started on lecture number
让我们开始讲课
two of four lecture sequences of shortest paths.
最短路径的四个讲座序列中的两个。
So, last time, we talked about a general structure
所以，上次我们讨论了一个通用结构
for a shortest path algorithm.
最短路径算法。
Today, we'll actually look at a concrete algorithm
今天，我们实际上将看一个具体的算法
that's due to Dijkstra.
那是由于Dijkstra。
Before we get to that, I want to do
在此之前，我想做
a little bit of a review of the concepts
回顾一下概念
that we covered in the lecture last week.
这是我们上周在讲座中介绍的内容。
In particular, we talked about this notion
特别是我们谈到了这个概念
of relaxation, which is a fundamental operation
放松，这是一项基本操作
in all shortest path algorithms.
在所有最短路径算法中。
And I want to go over that again.
我想再谈一遍。
We look at a couple of special cases
我们来看几个特殊情况
today, with respect to algorithms for shortest paths.
今天，关于最短路径的算法。
We look at a Directed Acyclic Graph.
我们看一个有向无环图。
Then your graph has no cycles in it.
那么您的图形中就没有循环。
Regardless of whether you have negative edges or not,
不管您是否有负面优势，
there's a straightforward algorithm
有一个简单的算法
that we look at to find shortest paths and DAGs.
我们将寻找最短的路径和DAG。
And then, we'll focus in on the case
然后，我们将专注于案例
where there are no negative edges.
没有消极的地方。
And talk about Dijkstra's algorithm.
并讨论Dijkstra的算法。
So, to start with the review, here's,
所以，从评论开始，这里是
really, a trivial example of a graph
确实，一个简单的图形示例
that we want to compute the shortest paths on.
我们要计算最短路径的路径。
And the numbers that are inside these vertices
这些顶点内的数字
are our priority values.
是我们的优先值。
So, think of d of v as the length of the current shortest
因此，将v的d视为当前最短的长度
path from the source, s, to v.
从源s到v的路径。
And, given the source, s, the length to the source is 0.
并且，在给定源s的情况下，到源的长度为0。
So d of s is 0.
因此s的d为0。
It starts at 0 and ends at 0.
它从0开始，到0结束。
And other ones, I initialized to infinity.
和其他的一样，我初始化为无穷大。
And through this process that we call relaxation,
通过这个我们称为放松的过程，
we can generally reduce these d values,
我们通常可以减少这些d值，
that are the lengths of the current shortest paths,
这是当前最短路径的长度，
down to what we call the delta values.
直到我们所说的增量值。
Which is the length of our shortest path.
这是我们最短路径的长度。
It may be unique.
它可能是唯一的。
It may not be unique.
它可能不是唯一的。
But you have to get the minimum value.
但是您必须获得最小值。
And then, all of the vertices have convergent values
然后，所有顶点都具有收敛值
of d that converge to delta.
的d收敛到delta。
Then, your algorithm is done.
然后，算法完成。
And one last thing that is important to reconstruct
最后一件对重建很重要的事情
the path is the notion of a predecessor and pi v
路径是前辈和pi v的概念
is the predecessor of v in the shortest path from s
在距离s最短的路径中是v的前身
to v. And you can follow this predecessor
诉v。您可以追随此前任
chain to reconstruct the shortest path,
链以重建最短路径，
once you've converged, and all of the values
一旦融合，所有的价值
are down to the delta s comma v. So, in this trivial example,
归结于delta s逗号v。因此，在这个琐碎的示例中，
you start with d of s being 0, d of a and d of b being infinity.
您以s的d为0，a的d和b的d为无穷大开始。
Let's put on it a few weights here.
让我们在这里加一些权重。
And what you do is potentially relax
而你要做的就是放松
the edges that go out of s.
s的边缘。
And this notion of relaxation, that I'll write out formally
这个放松的概念，我会正式写出来
in a minute-- we looked at it last time,
一分钟后-我们上次看了一下，
is a process of following this edge,
是遵循这一优势的过程，
and updating the d of a value.
并更新值的d。
And this infinity becomes 1 because you say, well,
这个无穷大变为1，因为你说，
if I start here with 0 and I add 1 to it, I get 1 here.
如果我从0开始并加1，则得到1。
Similarly, this infinity becomes 3.
同样，此无穷大为3。
And, at this point, you've relaxed the edges
并且，此时，您已经放松了边缘
that go out of s two these other two nodes, a and b.
从其他两个另外两个节点a和b中得出。
You're not quite done yet.
您尚未完成。
At this point, you could imagine that, at least in this example,
此时，您可以想象，至少在此示例中，
you found the shortest path to the vertex a.
您找到了到达顶点a的最短路径。
But it is, in fact, a path of length, 2, to vertex b.
但这实际上是到顶点b的长度为2的路径。
Right now, we think that the the current shortest path to b,
现在，我们认为当前通往b的最短路径是
after the first step of relaxing the edges from s,
在从s放松边缘的第一步之后，
happens to be 3.
碰巧是3。
But if you go like so, then you end up with the 2.
但是，如果您这样做，则最终得到的是2。
And, at this point, you're done.
至此，您已经完成。
Now we have to prove that any particular algorithm we put up
现在我们必须证明我们提出的任何特定算法
is going to converge to the delta values, and the algorithm
将收敛到增量值，并且算法
to terminate.
终止。
And then, we have to worry about the asymptotic complexity
然后，我们必须担心渐近复杂性
of the algorithm.
算法的
But that's the general overall flow.
但这就是总体流程。
And we look at, as I said, two algorithms today.
正如我说的，我们今天讨论两种算法。
Both special cases.
两种特殊情况。
One for DAGs and one for non-negative edges.
一种用于DAG，另一种用于非负边缘。
And we'll go through, and maybe not do a formal proof,
我们会仔细研究，也许不会做正式的证明，
but suddenly give you a strong intuition
但是突然间给你强烈的直觉
as to why these algorithms work.
这些算法为何起作用。
Any questions about this material?
对这个材料有任何疑问吗？
OK.
好。
So, what I want to do is give you
所以，我要做的就是给你
a sense for why this relaxation step is useful.
这种放松步骤为何有用的感觉。
But also, importantly, safe, or correct.
但同样重要的是，安全或正确的。
And recall that our basic relaxation operation, which
回想一下我们基本的放松操作
we did over here, as we updated the infinity value to 1
我们在这里做了，因为我们将无穷大值更新为1
and the 3 value to 2, et cetera, looks like this.
值3等于2，等等。
It says, if d of v is greater than d of u plus w u,v. Then,
它说，如果v的d大于u的d加wu，v。然后，
I'm going to update d of v to be d of u plus w u, v.
我将把v的d更新为u加wu，v的d。
You found a better way of reaching vertex v.
您找到了到达顶点v的更好方法。
A shorter way.
一种较短的方法。
And this way happens to be going through the vertex, u.
而且这种方式恰好通过了顶点u。
So you update not only the priority value, but also
因此，您不仅可以更新优先级值，还可以更新
the predecessor relationship.
前辈关系。
All right?
好吧？
That's the relaxation step.
那是放松的步骤。
Now, I want to be able to show that relaxation is safe.
现在，我希望能够证明放松是安全的。
What do I mean by that?
那是什么意思
Well, I want to make sure that I never relax an edge
好吧，我想确保自己永远不会放松
and somehow do something wrong, which
并以某种方式做错了
gets me a value that's less than delta s v.
给我的值小于delta s v。
I want to be able to converge from the top.
我希望能够从顶部收敛。
I want to be able to start with these infinity values
我希望能够从这些无限值开始
because I don't have a path to this particular vertex,
因为我没有通往这个特定顶点的路径，
and continually reduce the values of the priorities.
并不断降低优先级的价值。
And then get down to delta, the correct values, and don't go,
然后求出正确的增量值，别走了，
I don't want to go any further.
我不想再走了。
All right?
好吧？
Because, if I get below, then you're talking about,
因为，如果我跌倒了，那么您在谈论，
essentially, you may be able to get back up,
从本质上讲，您也许可以复活，
but that is not the kind of algorithm that we want.
但这不是我们想要的那种算法。
At least, algorithms we look at here.
至少，我们在这里查看算法。
And that is dangerous.
那很危险。
So we want relaxation to be safe.
因此，我们希望放松是安全的。
And we can fairly easily prove a simple lemma,
我们可以很容易地证明一个简单的引理，
using induction, that says that the relaxation
使用归纳法，即放松
operation-- and it doesn't matter
操作-没关系
what sequence you relax things.
你放松什么顺序。
This is a fairly powerful lemma that
这是一个相当强大的引理
says that if you have an algorithm that uses relaxation,
说如果您有使用松弛的算法，
and that's the only way of updating these d values,
这是更新这些d值的唯一方法，
then it's safe.
那很安全
You're not going to get a wrong, shortest path value.
您不会得到错误的最短路径值。
Either at the end of the algorithm
在算法末尾
or at any time during the running, or the execution,
或在跑步或执行期间的任何时候，
of this algorithm.
该算法。
OK?
好？
So the relaxation operation algorithm
所以松弛运算算法
maintains the invariant that d of v
维持v的d不变
is greater than or equal to delta s, v for all vertices.
对于所有顶点，均大于或等于delta s，v。
OK?
好？
So that's a powerful lemma.
所以这是一个强大的引理。
It's a fairly straightforward lemma to prove.
这是一个相当简单的引理可以证明。
But it's an important lemma.
但这是一个重要的引理。
It tells us that we can create the generic structure
它告诉我们可以创建通用结构
of the shortest path algorithm that I talked about last week.
我上周讨论的最短路径算法。
It says, pick an edge.
它说，挑一个边缘。
Relax it.
放轻松
Pick another edge.
选择另一个优势。
Relax it.
放轻松
And hopefully everything will work out
希望一切都会解决
and you'll get your delta values.
然后您将获得增量值。
And what this lemma says is, you'll
这个引理说的是，你会
never get something in the middle that
永远不会在中间得到任何东西
is less than your shortest path value.
小于最短路径值。
And if you keep running over for long enough time,
如果你继续跑了足够长的时间，
depending on the particular heuristic
取决于特定的启发式
that you use for selecting the edges,
用于选择边缘的
your algorithm will eventually terminate.
您的算法最终将终止。
And, hopefully, it'll run in polynomial time.
而且，希望它将在多项式时间内运行。
So, how do we prove this?
那么，我们如何证明这一点呢？
I'm going to do about half of it,
我要做大约一半
then try and get you to finish it.
然后尝试让您完成它。
So it's by induction on the number of steps,
所以是归纳为步骤数，
in the sense that we are going to essentially assume that d
在某种意义上，我们将基本上假设d
of u is greater than or equal to delta s,u.
u的值大于或等于delta s，u。
And we're going to do this relaxation operation.
我们将执行此放松操作。
So it's like a base case is that this is correct.
因此，这就像一个基本情况，是正确的。
And now we want to show that the relaxation operation doesn't
现在我们想证明松弛操作不会
make d of v incorrect.
使v的d不正确。
So, that's the inductive hypothesis.
因此，这就是归纳假设。
Now, we can say by the triangle inequality
现在，我们可以通过三角不等式说
that I talked about late in last week's lecture,
在上周的演讲中我谈到的是
you have delta s, v less than or equal to delta s comma
您有delta s，v小于或等于delta s逗号
u plus delta u comma v. And what is that?
你加上三角洲逗号，那是什么？
Well, that just says, if I have something like this,
好吧，这就是说，如果我有这样的事情，
that I have s.
我有。
Let's call this u and v.
我们称这个为u和v。
This is not an edge between s and v. It's a path.
这不是s和v之间的边，而是一条路径。
It could be a single edge.
它可以是单个边缘。
But we think of this as a path between s
但是我们认为这是s之间的一条路径
and v. This is a path between s and u.
和v。这是s和u之间的路径。
This is a path between u and v.
这是u和v之间的路径。
And, in particular, if there's a way
特别是如果有办法
of getting from s to u and u to v that happens to be shorter
从s到u和从u到v的过程恰好较短
then the best way of getting from s to v,
那么从s到v的最佳方法，
well, that's a contradiction.
好吧，这是一个矛盾。
OK?
好？
Because this is the shortest way of getting from s to v.
因为这是从s到v的最短方法。
And it has no constraints over the number of edges
而且它对边的数量没有限制
that it incorporates.
它纳入。
And so, by definition, the shortest way
因此，按照定义，最短的方法
of getting from s to v is either some direct way.
从s到v的一种直接方法。
Maybe there's a single edge.
也许只有一个优势。
Or it may go through this vertex, u.
否则它可能会穿过此顶点u。
All right?
好吧？
So that's the triangle inequality.
这就是三角形不等式。
Notice that, what I have here, is something
注意，我在这里有一些东西
where going from s, to a, to b is actually
从s到a到b的位置实际上是
shorter than going from s to b.
比从s到b短。
But these are single edges we're talking about.
但是这些都是我们正在谈论的单一方面。
These are weights we're talking about.
这些是我们正在谈论的权重。
And there's no contradiction here
这里没有矛盾
because all this says is that, what I want to see here
因为这就是我想在这里看到的
is delta s comma b is going to be 2.
是delta s逗号b将为2。
OK?
好？
Initially, I may be starting out with infinity and 3
最初，我可能会以无穷大和3开始
for the d values.
对于d值。
But the delta value, which is the shortest way
但是增量值，这是最短的方法
of getting to b, happens to go through a.
到达b的过程，碰巧经历了a。
And so, if you use that, then the triangle inequality
因此，如果使用它，那么三角形不等式
makes sense.
说得通。
So don't get confused when you see pictures
所以看图片时不要困惑
like this, where the weights don't obey the triangle
这样，权重不服从三角形
inequality.
不等式。
The triangle inequality has to do with the shortest paths, not
三角不等式与最短路径有关，而不是
the single edge ways.
单边方式。
OK?
好？
So, that's half the proof here.
所以，这是这里的一半证明。
What I've done is assumed that d of u is correct.
我所做的假设是假设d是正确的。
And I've used the triangle inequality.
而且我使用了三角形不等式。
And I've just written this down.
我刚刚写下来。
Now, someone do the last step, or the second to last step,
现在，有人进行了最后一步，或者倒数第二步，
of this proof.
这个证明。
Anybody?
有人吗
What can I say now, given that what I have here.
鉴于我在这里拥有什么，我现在能说什么。
Look at these two values.
看这两个值。
What can I say about these values?
我能说些什么？
How can I prove what I want to prove,
我该如何证明我想证明的东西，
which is, basically, delta of s comma v should be less than
基本上，s的差值v应该小于
or equal to d of v?
等于v的d？
OK.
好。
That's what I want to show.
那就是我想展示的。
I've just written another way here.
我在这里写了另一种方式。
How do I do that?
我怎么做？
Anyone?
任何人？
What can I substitute for-- there's a less than operator,
我可以替代什么-少于运算符，
which means that I can replace things over here.
这意味着我可以替换这里的东西。
Yeah.
是的
AUDIENCE: If you, like, you have a [INAUDIBLE]?
听众：如果您喜欢，您有[听不清]吗？
PROFESSOR: Ah.
教授：嗯。
Excellent.
优秀的。
So the first thing is, I could put d of u over here, right?
所以第一件事是，我可以把你放在这里，对吗？
Less than or equal to d of u.
小于或等于u的d。
And the reason I can do that is because d of u
我之所以能够做到这一点，是因为你的d
is greater then delta s comma u.
大于delta逗号。
So that's cool, right?
太酷了吧？
Sorry, delta.
抱歉，三角洲。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Delta s comma u.
三角洲逗号
Thank you.
谢谢。
And so, that's what I got here.
所以，这就是我在这里得到的。
What else?
还有什么？
Yeah?
是啊
AUDIENCE: You replace delta u, v with w u, v.
受众：您将u，v替换为wu，v。
PROFESSOR: I can replace delta u, v with w, u,
教授：我可以用w，u代替u，v
v. Exactly right.
v。完全正确。
Exactly right.
非常正确。
Great.
大。
That deserves a cushion.
那值得缓冲。
I think you already have one.
我想你已经有一个。
Yep.
是的
Oh, man.
天啊。
I should have not-- so you get that because I messed up.
我不应该-因为我搞砸了，所以您明白了。
Seems like you need to get-- whoa.
似乎您需要获取-哇。
Hey.
嘿。
OK.
好。
You get one because I hit you on the head.
你得到一个，因为我打你的头。
All right.
好吧。
And this time, I'll just save.
而这次，我将保存。
I'm running out of cushions here.
我的座垫不多了。
But I've got some in my office.
但是我办公室里有一些。
All right.
好吧。
So that's it.
就是这样了。
That's the proof.
那就是证明。
OK?
好？
Fairly straightforward.
非常坦率的。
You get to the point where you want
您到达想要的地步
to apply the triangle inequality.
应用三角形不等式。
You simply look at each of these terms and, by induction
您只需看一下每个术语，并通过归纳法
hypothesis, you could put d,u here.
假设，您可以将d，u放在这里。
And, I just talked about the weights,
而且，我刚刚谈到了重量，
and so on, and so forth.
等等等等。
And you know that w u,v, which is a direct way,
而且您知道wu，v是直接的方法，
a single edge way, of getting to a node,
到达节点的单边方法
has to be greater than the shortest path.
必须大于最短路径。
Like here, this 3 value is a direct way
像这里一样，这3个值是直接的方法
of getting from s to b.
从s到b的关系。
And, in this case, it's greater than the shortest
而且，在这种情况下，它大于最短的
path, which is of length 2.
路径，长度为2。
But it can never be smaller than the shortest path.
但是它永远不能小于最短路径。
And so, once we have that here, we can essentially say,
因此，一旦我们在这里有了，我们就可以说，
we know that delta s, v is less than or equal to d u plus d v.
我们知道delta s，v小于或等于du plus d v。
Which implies, of course, that this is simply--
当然，这意味着，这仅仅是-
once we are done with the relaxation step-- that
一旦我们完成放松步骤-
equals d v. This part here equals d v. OK?
等于d v。这部分等于d v。好吗？
That's how that works.
就是这样。
So that's good news.
这是个好消息。
We have a relaxation algorithm that is safe.
我们有一个安全的松弛算法。
We can now arbitrarily, and we'll
现在，我们可以任意选择，
do this for all of algorithms we look at, really.
确实针对我们研究的所有算法执行此操作。
At least in 006, for shortest paths.
至少在006中，用于最短路径。
Which applies some sequence of relaxations.
其中应用了一些松弛顺序。
And, depending on the special case of the problem,
并且，根据问题的特殊情况，
we're going to apply these things in different ways
我们将以不同的方式应用这些东西
to get the most efficient algorithm.
以获得最有效的算法。
All right?
好吧？
So, we can now do algorithms.
因此，我们现在可以执行算法。
Let's look at DAGs first.
首先让我们看一下DAG。
So, DAG stands for Directed Acyclic Graphs.
因此，DAG代表有向无环图。
So that means we can't have cycles.
所以这意味着我们不能有循环。
So we can't have negative cycles.
所以我们不能有负周期。
So that's why this is an interesting special case.
这就是为什么这是一个有趣的特殊情况。
It makes things a little bit easier for us
它使我们的工作更轻松
because we don't have to worry about negative cycles.
因为我们不必担心负周期。
We're actually going to look at DAGs
我们实际上将研究DAG
that have negative edges in them.
里面有消极的边缘。
All right?
好吧？
So, we're allowed to have negative edges in these DAGs.
因此，允许我们在这些DAG中使用负边缘。
But we don't have negative cycles.
但是我们没有负周期。
And, as I said last time, it's not
而且，正如我上次说的，
the negative edges that cause a problem.
引起问题的负边缘。
If you only go through at negative edge once,
如果只在负边缘经历一次，
you can just subtract that value.
您可以减去该值。
And it's cool.
而且很酷。
It's only when you get into a situation
只有当你陷入困境时
where you're going through a negative edge,
你正在经历一个消极的边缘，
a negative cycle.
负循环。
And you can just iterate through them to get to minus infinity.
您可以遍历它们以达到负无穷大。
And you have an indeterminate shortest path value.
并且您有不确定的最短路径值。
So the way this is going to work-- if you ever
所以这将是可行的-如果您愿意
have a DAG, by the way, the first thing you want to try--
顺便说一句，有一个DAG，您想尝试的第一件事-
and this is certainly true in your problem set--
在您的问题集中肯定是这样-
when there's a question, try to topologically sort it.
遇到问题时，请尝试对其进行拓扑排序。
OK?
好？
It's a fine hammer to use, when you have a DAG.
装有DAG时，可以使用这把锤子。
And it's not an exception here.
在这里也不例外。
To do shortest paths, we're going
要走最短的路，我们要
to topologically sort the DAG.
对DAG进行拓扑排序。
And the path from u to v implies that u
从u到v的路径意味着u
is before v in the ordering.
在排序中位于v之前。
And, once you do that, you have this linear.
而且，一旦执行此操作，就具有线性关系。
And I'll show you an example.
我会给你看一个例子。
You have this linear ordering.
您具有此线性顺序。
And we're just going to go through, in order,
我们将按顺序进行
from left to right, relaxing these edges.
从左到右，放松这些边缘。
And we're going to get our shortest
而且我们要做到最短
paths for all the vertices.
所有顶点的路径。
So, the second and last step is, one pass, left to right,
因此，第二个也是最后一个步骤，从左到右，
over the vertices, in topologically sorted order.
在顶点上，按照拓扑排序的顺序排列。
And we're going to relax each edge that
我们将放松每个方面
leaves the particular vertex we are
离开特定的顶点
trying to process right now.
现在尝试进行处理。
And so, we know topological sorting is order v plus e,
因此，我们知道拓扑排序是v加上e，
includes depth-first search.
包括深度优先搜索。
And this pass over the vertices, you're touching each vertex.
而这越过了顶点，您正在触摸每个顶点。
And you're touching every edge a constant number of times.
而您触摸每个边缘的次数是固定的。
In this case, once.
在这种情况下，一次。
So this is our first special case shortest path algorithm.
因此，这是我们的第一个特例最短路径算法。
And that takes order v plus e time.
这需要订单v加上e的时间。
All right?
好吧？
Why does this work?
为什么这样做？
And just one little interesting aspect
还有一个有趣的方面
of this, which is related to a DAG.
这与DAG有关。
And the relationship between the DAG and the particular starting
以及DAG与特定起点之间的关系
vertex that we're going to be looking at.
我们要关注的顶点。
So, this is an example.
因此，这是一个示例。
Suppose I have a DAG like this.
假设我有一个像这样的DAG。
And I marked this vertex as s.
我将此顶点标记为s。
And I want to find the shortest path from s
我想找到s的最短路径
to these other nodes that are a and b.
到这些其他节点a和b。
Well, they don't exist, right?
好吧，它们不存在，对不对？
So, in this case, I'm going to have a shortest
所以，在这种情况下，我将最短
path to a being infinity and shortest path to b
通往无穷大的路径和通往b的最短路径
being infinity.
无限
And this is a trivial example.
这是一个简单的例子。
So, this algorithm is general.
因此，该算法是通用的。
It doesn't say anything about what the starting vertex is.
它没有说明起始顶点是什么。
Right?
对？
It should work for any choice of starting vertex.
它应该适用于任何起始顶点选择。
The nice thing is that you can do the topological sort.
令人高兴的是，您可以进行拓扑排序。
And then you can commit to what the starting vertex is.
然后，您可以承诺起始顶点是什么。
And you can go off, and you can say, from this starting vertex,
然后，您可以从这个起始顶点出发，
I'm going to go and compute the shortest paths
我要去计算最短的路径
to the other vertices that I can actually reach.
到我实际可以到达的其他顶点。
OK?
好？
So let's say that you had a DAG that looks like this.
假设您有一个看起来像这样的DAG。
All right, once you've topologically sorted it,
好吧，一旦您对它进行了拓扑排序，
you can always draw a DAG in linear form.
您可以始终以线性形式绘制DAG。
That's a nice thing.
很好
I'm going to put edge weights down in a minute.
我将在一分钟内降低边缘权重。
All right.
好吧。
So that's my DAG.
这就是我的DAG。
Let's see.
让我们来看看。
5, 3, 2, 6, 7, 4, 2, minus 1, minus 2.
5，3，2，6，7，4，4，负1，负2。
So that's my DAG.
这就是我的DAG。
And I've drawn it in topologically sorted form.
我已经按照拓扑排序的形式绘制了它。
And I go left to right.
我从左到右。
Now, let's say that, at this point, I get to step two.
现在，让我们说到这一步，我进入第二步。
And I want to find shortest paths.
我想找到最短的路径。
Now, I have to say, what is my source?
现在，我不得不说，我的来源是什么？
And, if I just happen to have this as my source,
而且，如果我只是碰巧以此为来源，
well, there's nothing to do here.
好吧，这里无事可做。
There's no edges that go out of this.
没有任何余地。
And so that means that everything to the left of me
所以这意味着我左边的一切
is infinity.
是无穷大。
OK?
好？
So the first thing that you do is,
因此，您要做的第一件事是，
you say, find the source that corresponds
你说，找到对应的来源
to the starting vertex.
到起始顶点。
And let's say, this is the starting vertex, in this case.
假设在这种情况下，这是起始顶点。
Which I'll mark in bold.
我将以粗体标记。
So that's my starting vertex.
这就是我的起点。
I'll take a nontrivial case.
我将处理一个不平凡的案件。
And everything to the left is going
左边的一切都在进行
to get marked with infinity.
标记无穷大。
And now, I've got to do some work on relaxation.
现在，我必须做一些放松的工作。
And I'm not going to get the shortest path instantly
而且我不会立即获得最短的路径
for a particular vertex, once I get to it, because there
对于特定的顶点，一旦到达该顶点，因为
may be better ways of getting there.
可能是到达那里的更好方法。
And especially if I have negative edges.
特别是如果我有消极的一面。
And that's certainly possible, that a longer length path
当然，这可能是更长的路径
is going to be the shortest path.
将是最短的路径。
But what I'll do is take s.
但是我要做的是s。
And I'm going to relax edges that emanate from s.
我将放松从s发出的边缘。
And so, step one, all of these are
因此，第一步，所有这些都是
going to be infinity to start with.
首先将是无穷大。
So everything is infinity.
所以一切都是无限的。
The ones to the left stay infinity.
左边的那些保持无限。
The ones to the right are going to be reachable.
右边的那些将是可及的。
And you're going to update those values.
您将更新这些值。
And so, when you go like so, this becomes 2.
因此，当您像这样前进时，该值为2。
This becomes 6.
这变成6。
As I follow that.
按照我的指示。
And I'm done with this vertex, s.
我已经完成了这个顶点s。
And this is what I have.
这就是我所拥有的。
2 and 6.
2和6。
So the next step is to get to this vertex.
所以下一步就是到达这个顶点。
Let's call that the vertex a.
我们称顶点为a。
And I'm going relax the edges going out of a.
我要放松a的边缘。
And, when I go out of a, I get 2 plus 7
而且，当我淘汰a时，我得到2加7
is 9, which is greater than 6.
是9，大于6。
So there's no reason to update that.
因此，没有理由进行更新。
2 plus 4 is less than infinity.
2加4小于无穷大。
And so, that's 6.
就是6。
2 plus 2 gives me 4 here.
2加2给我4。
And so on and so forth.
等等等等。
So then, now I'm done with vertex a.
因此，现在我完成了顶点a。
If this vertex is b, then I have a value of 6 for this.
如果这个顶点是b，那么我的值为6。
And 6 minus 1 is less than 6.
6减1小于6。
So this becomes 5.
这样就变成5。
And 5 minus 2-- well, that's the next step after that.
5减2-好吧，这是之后的下一步。
I haven't put-- this is a 1.
我没有放-这是1。
And so 6 plus 1 is 7.
所以6加1是7
But that's greater than 4.
但这大于4。
So we don't have to anything there.
因此，我们不必在那儿做任何事情。
So the final values that I end up getting are 3 for this one.
因此，我最终得到的最终值是3。
So this is the final value.
所以这是最终值。
5 is the final value here.
5是此处的最终值。
6 is the final value here.
此处的最终值为6。
2 is the final value here.
此处的最终值为2。
And that one is 0.
那是0。
And this stays infinity.
并且这保持无限。
OK?
好？
So fairly straightforward.
非常简单。
Do a topological sort.
进行拓扑排序。
Find the starting point.
找到起点。
And then run all the way to the right.
然后一直向右运行。
Interestingly, this is actually a really simple example
有趣的是，这实际上是一个非常简单的示例
of dynamic programming, which we'll talk about
动态编程，我们将讨论
in gory detail, later in November.
详细信息，十一月下旬。
But what I have here is the simplest special case
但是我这里是最简单的特殊情况
of a graph that has an order of v e [INAUDIBLE]
阶为ve的图的[听不清]
shortest path algorithm.
最短路径算法。
And the reason for that is we don't have cycles.
原因是我们没有周期。
All right?
好吧？
Any questions about this?
对此有任何疑问吗？
People buy this?
人们买这个？
It works?
有用？
OK.
好。
So, we've got one algorithm under our belt.
因此，我们掌握了一种算法。
And we look at, really, a more interesting case
我们来看一个更有趣的案例
because most graphs are going to have cycles in them.
因为大多数图形都将包含循环。
But we will stay with the special case
但是我们会保留特殊情况
of no negative edges, now.
现在没有负面影响。
All right?
好吧？
So Dijkstra's algorithm doesn't work for negative edges.
因此Dijkstra的算法不适用于负边缘。
So it's different.
所以不一样。
This algorithm is not subsumed by Dijkstra.
Dijkstra不包含此算法。
That's important to understand.
了解这一点很重要。
So Dijkstra's algorithm works for graphs with cycles.
因此Dijkstra的算法适用于带有循环的图。
But all of the edge ways have to be either 0 or positive.
但是所有边缘方式都必须为0或正数。
This algorithm works for DAGs that can have negative edges.
该算法适用于可能具有负边缘的DAG。
But you can't have cycles.
但是你不能有周期。
So both of these algorithms have their place under the sun.
因此，这两种算法都在阳光下占有一席之地。
So, let's take a look at Dijkstra's algorithm.
因此，让我们看一下Dijkstra的算法。
Actually, I guess I have a demo.
实际上，我想我有一个演示。
So, the one demo we have in 6006.
因此，我们在6006中有一个演示。
[INAUDIBLE] Dijkstra is a very straightforward algorithm.
[听不清] Dijkstra是一种非常简单的算法。
It's not trivial to prove its correctness.
证明其正确性并非易事。
But from a standpoint of coding, from a standpoint
但是从编码的角度来看
of understanding the flow, it's a very straightforward
了解流程，这非常简单
algorithm.
算法。
One of the reasons why that's the case
发生这种情况的原因之一
is because it's a greedy algorithm.
是因为这是一种贪婪算法。
It does things incrementally, maximizing the benefit,
它会逐步执行任务，从而使收益最大化，
as you will.
随你便。
And intuitively builds the shortest paths.
并直观地构建最短路径。
And it goes vertex by vertex.
它逐个顶点。
So here's a demo of Dijkstra, which,
这是Dijkstra的演示，
the reason I want to show you this,
我想给你看这个的原因
is because it will give you some intuition as to why Dijkstra
是因为它将使您对为什么Dijkstra有一些直觉
works.
作品。
Now, some points of note.
现在，一些注意事项。
I can't tilt this more than about this much
我不能超过此程度
because then these balls will fall off.
因为这些球会掉下来。
So, cameraman, can you get this?
那么，摄影师，你能得到这个吗？
All right?
好吧？
For posterity.
为了后代。
So I got an undirected graph here, right?
所以我在这里得到了无向图，对吗？
And each of these things are nodes.
这些东西都是节点。
The balls are the nodes of the vertices.
球是顶点的节点。
And I've drawn the picture over there.
我在那边画了画。
And G stands for green.
G代表绿色。
And Y stands for yellow, et cetera.
Y代表黄色，等等。
So, this graph is essentially what I have up there.
所以，这张图本质上就是我在那里的东西。
And I've put strings connecting these balls, associated
我把连接这些球的弦放进去
with the weights that you see up there.
与您在那里看到的重量。
So, if I got this right, the string
所以，如果我说对了，那么字符串
that's connecting the green ball to the yellow ball up on top
将绿色球连接到顶部的黄色球
is 19 centimeters.
是19厘米。
And so on and so forth for these other ones.
等等，以此类推。
All right?
好吧？
So, that's Dijkstra.
那就是Dijkstra。
And what do you think I have to do
你觉得我该怎么办
to compute shortest paths, mechanically speaking?
机械地计算最短路径？
What do you think I have to do?
您认为我该怎么办？
Yeah, someone.
是的，有人。
AUDIENCE: Pick up the green ball and just--
听众：拿起绿色的球，然后-
PROFESSOR: Pick up the ball and lift it up.
教授：拿起球并将其抬起。
That's right.
那就对了。
Good.
好。
It's worth a cushion.
值得缓冲。
All right, so, let's all this works.
好吧，让我们完成所有这些工作。
So, first, let me show you by those values that I have there.
因此，首先，让我通过我那里的价值观向您展示。
If the green ball is the starting vertex, then
如果绿色球是起始顶点，则
the shortest path to the purple vertex, p, is 7.
紫色顶点的最短路径p为7。
And that's the closest node to G.
那是最接近G的节点
And then, the next closest node is
然后，下一个最近的节点是
the blue one, which is b, which is 12.
蓝色的一个，即b，即12。
7 plus 5.
7加5。
And so on and so forth.
等等等等。
And so, if this all works, and I haven't tried this out,
因此，如果这一切都可行，而我还没有尝试过，
because this is a one use demo.
因为这是一个一次性演示。
Once I pull this up, the strings get so tangled up,
一旦我把它拉起来，弦就变得如此纠结，
it doesn't work anymore.
它不再工作了。
All right?
好吧？
So that's why I had to do all of this, lug these over.
所以这就是为什么我必须做所有这些，把这些都拖过去。
Otherwise, it'd be-- so this is not
否则会-所以这不是
a computer reversible kind of thing.
一种计算机可逆的东西。
So, if you want to code Dijkstra up.
因此，如果您想对Dijkstra进行编码。
OK, so if I just lift it up, and if I do that,
好，所以如果我把它抬起来，如果这样做，
and if I tilt it in the right direction.
如果我朝正确的方向倾斜。
Yeah.
是的
I want to that.
我想要那个。
So you can see that this is a little bit of fudging going on
所以您可以看到这有点令人困惑
here, with respect to getting this right.
在这里，关于正确的选择。
But you see green is up on top.
但是您会看到绿色在最上面。
And what is the next one you see?
您接下来会看到什么？
AUDIENCE: Purple.
听众：紫色。
PROFESSOR: Purple.
教授：紫色。
That's good.
那很好。
What's the next one you see?
您看到的下一个是什么？
AUDIENCE: Blue.
听众：蓝色。
PROFESSOR: Blue.
教授：蓝色。
That's good.
那很好。
Y, and then R. And strings that are taught,
是Y，然后是R。
that have tension in them, are the predecessor vertices, OK?
它们之间有张力吗，前一个顶点好吗？
That's the pie.
那是馅饼。
All right?
好吧？
So, again, I computed the shortest paths, right?
所以，我又计算出最短路径，对吗？
Mechanically.
机械上。
And, if I could have a way of measuring the tension
而且，如果我有办法测量张力
on the strings, I have my pie, my predecessor relationship,
在弦上，我有我的馅饼，我的前任关系，
as well.
也一样
All right?
好吧？
Now, let's see if this works.
现在，让我们看看是否可行。
This works, right?
这样行对不对
So, if the second thing doesn't work, don't hold it against me.
因此，如果第二件事不起作用，请不要反对我。
But, let's say if I take R, and I lift it up like that.
但是，假设我拿了R，然后像这样将它提起。
Yikes.
kes。
So, R, followed by Y, followed by B, followed by P,
因此，R，Y，Y，B，P
followed by G.
其次是G。
Hey.
嘿。
Come on.
来吧。
All right?
好吧？
This works.
这可行。
Thank you.
谢谢。
All right.
好吧。
So there's actually a reason why I did that demo.
所以实际上是我进行该演示的原因。
There's a greedy algorithm here.
这里有一个贪心算法。
And, I guess, greedy is gravity.
而且，我想，贪婪是引力。
Right?
对？
Gravity is greedy.
重力是贪婪的。
So, obviously, the reason why those balls are hanging
所以，很明显，这些球悬挂的原因
is because they have weight.
是因为他们有体重。
And they have gravity.
他们有重力。
And you can imagine that you could now-- people in physics.
您可以想象，您现在可以-物理学家。
I don't know anybody majoring in physics.
我不认识物理学专业的人。
Anyone double majoring in physics or something here?
有人在读物理学双专业吗？
All right.
好吧。
So, you know your Newton's laws of mechanics.
因此，您知道您的牛顿力学定律。
And you know about gravity, and all of that.
您知道重力，以及所有这些。
So you can imagine that you said, you know,
所以你可以想象你说，你知道，
the heck with all this priority queue stuff in the problem set.
问题集中所有这些优先级队列内容的问题。
In the algorithm that we're going
在我们要使用的算法中
to be talking about for Dijkstra,
为Dijkstra谈论，
I'm going to do a kinetic simulation of shortest paths
我将对最短路径进行动力学模拟
in order to get the actual values of these shortest paths.
为了获得这些最短路径的实际值。
OK?
好？
Now, that would be cool.
现在，那将很酷。
But it'd be horribly slow.
但这太慢了。
And so, the Dijkstra algorithm we're going to be talking about
因此，我们将要讨论的Dijkstra算法
is going to just compute the steady state, corresponding
将只计算稳态，对应
to the closest vertex that is closest to G. All right?
到最接近G的最近顶点。好吗？
So Dijkstra, the algorithm, the intuition behind it,
所以Dijkstra，算法，其背后的直觉，
is that it's going to greedily construct shortest paths.
是它会贪婪地构建最短路径。
And it's going to be starting with G,
它将从G开始
which is your source vertex.
这是您的源顶点。
And then, the first thing that it's
然后，第一件事是
going to process, and find the shortest path to
进行处理，并找到最短的路径
is going to be the purple vertex.
将成为紫色顶点。
And then the blue.
然后是蓝色。
And then the yellow.
然后是黄色。
And then the red.
然后是红色。
All right?
好吧？
So it actually mimics, to some extent, this demo.
因此，它实际上在某种程度上模仿了这个演示。
All right?
好吧？
So, let's take a look at the pseudocode for Dijkstra.
因此，让我们看一下Dijkstra的伪代码。
So, g is your graph.
因此，g是您的图表。
w are the weights.
w是权重。
Small s is the starting vertex.
小s是起始顶点。
We're going to initialize g and s, which means we just mark
我们将初始化g和s，这意味着我们只是标记
s a starting vertex.
一个起始顶点。
And we're going to also have this capital S, that I'll
而且我们还要有这个资本S
use these little bars to differentiate from small s.
使用这些小条与小s区分。
So this is a set.
所以这是一个集合。
Capital S is a set.
大写S是一组。
And we're going to initialize that to null.
我们将其初始化为null。
And there's another set called Q,
还有另一个叫Q的集合
which is initialized to the entire set of vertices.
初始化为整个顶点集。
And all this means is that, initially, we
而所有这些意味着，最初，我们
haven't done any processing.
尚未进行任何处理。
And we don't know the shortest paths to any vertex
而且我们不知道通往任何顶点的最短路径
because this set of vertices is null.
因为这组顶点为null。
And Q is the set of vertices that need to be processed.
Q是需要处理的一组顶点。
And, as we start processing vertices from Q,
并且，当我们开始处理Q的顶点时，
we're going to move them to capital S.
我们将把它们移到首都S。
And they're going to contain the set of vertices
它们将包含一组顶点
that we know the shortest paths to already.
我们已经知道最短的路径。
And that's the invariant in this algorithm.
这就是该算法的不变性。
s is going to contain the set of vertices
s将包含一组顶点
that we know the shortest paths to.
我们知道最短的路径。
And so, Dijkstra is a little while loop
所以，Dijkstra有点循环
that says, while they're vertices
也就是说，虽然它们是顶点
that need to be processed, then I'm going to take u.
需要处理的东西，然后我带你去。
And I'm going to extract-min from Q.
我将从Q中提取分钟数。
And this is going to delete u from Q.
这将从Q中删除u。
And this initialization-- and this
这个初始化-还有这个
is a small s here-- is going to set d of s to be 0.
在这里是小s-将s的d设置为0。
That's all this initialization does.
这就是初始化的全部工作。
Because that's all we know.
因为这就是我们所知道的。
We have a starting vertex.
我们有一个起始顶点。
And we know that the shortest path to the starting vertex,
我们知道到达起始顶点的最短路径
from the starting vertex, is 0.
从起始顶点开始为0。
So, all that means is that, all of the other ones
所以，这意味着所有其他
have infinity values.
具有无穷大值。
So, at this very first step, it makes sense
因此，在第一步中，这很有意义
that extract-min Q is going to pull
提取最小Q将拉
the starting vertex, small s, out.
起始顶点，小s，出。
And is going to assign it to this u value.
并将其分配给此u值。
And we're going to set s to be-- capital
我们将设置为-资本
S-- to be capital S union u.
S--成为资本S Union u。
And then, all we have to do is relax the edges from the vertex
然后，我们要做的就是放宽顶点的边缘
that we just added.
我们刚刚添加的。
So, for each vertex, v belonging to adjacent
因此，对于每个顶点，v属于相邻的
s, so that you can reach from u.
s，以便您可以从u到达。
We relax u, v, w.
我们放松你，v，w。
All right?
好吧？
That's it.
而已。
That's Dijkstra.
那是迪克斯特拉。
It's a greedy algorithm.
这是一个贪婪的算法。
It's iterative.
这是迭代的。
And the reason it's greedy is because of this step here.
贪婪的原因是因为这里的这一步。
It's just picking the min priority
只是选择最小优先级
from the un-processed vertices, Q. And, essentially,
从未经处理的顶点Q
claiming that this min value is something that you already
声称这是您已经拥有的最小值
computed the shortest paths for.
计算出最短路径。
So, when you're putting something into S,
因此，当您将某物放入S中时，
you're saying, I'm done.
你是说，我完成了。
I know the shortest path to this particular vertex.
我知道到达此特定顶点的最短路径。
And I need to now process it, in the sense that I
从某种意义上说，我现在需要对其进行处理
have to relax the edges that are coming out of this vertex.
必须放松从该顶点出来的边缘。
And update the priority values because relax
并更新优先级值，因为放松
is going to go change the d values, as we know,
我们将要更改d值，
corresponding to the vertex, v. It might change the value.
对应于顶点v。它可能会更改值。
It might not.
可能不会。
But there's a possibility that it would.
但是有可能会。
And you're going to do this for all of the edges
而您将为所有的边缘做到这一点
that are emanating out of the vertex, u.
从顶点发出的
And so you may be changing a bunch of different priority
因此，您可能会更改许多不同的优先级
values.
价值观。
So the next time around, you will
所以下一次，你会
get a different minimum priority vertex.
得到一个不同的最小优先级顶点。
For two reasons.
有两个原因。
One is that you've extracted out the minimum priority vertex.
一种是您已经提取了最小优先级顶点。
You've deleted it from Q. And the second reason
您已将其从Q中删除。第二个原因
is that these priority values change
这些优先级值改变了吗
as you go through the loop.
当您经历循环时。
All right?
好吧？
And so, in our demo, essentially what happened was,
因此，在我们的演示中，本质上是
the first time, the process of lifting the green vertex,
第一次，提升绿色顶点的过程，
corresponding to choosing it as a starting vertex.
对应于选择它作为起始顶点。
And the first thing that was closest
而最接近的第一件事
to it, which had the taught string hanging from it,
上面悬挂着教taught的绳子，
has the min priority value.
具有最小优先级值。
And you pull that out.
然后你把它拔出来。
And then so on and so forth, as you go down.
然后下去，依此类推，下去。
And I'm not going to go through and prove this.
我不会去证明这一点。
But it's certainly something that is worth reading.
但这当然值得一读。
It's half of page proof, maybe a page in CLRS.
这是页面证明的一半，也许是CLRS中的页面。
And you should read the proof for Dijkstra,
您应该阅读Dijkstra的证明，
the formal proof for Dijkstra.
Dijkstra的正式证明。
Which just, essentially, does all the accounting
本质上，所有会计工作
and gets things right.
并把事情做好。
And uses the lemma that we have, with respect to the relaxation
并使用关于松弛的引理
operation being safe.
操作安全。
OK?
好？
Any questions about Dijkstra?
对Dijkstra有疑问吗？
Or about the pseudocode, in particular?
还是关于伪代码？
I guess you guys are going to code this at some point.
我想你们会在某个时候编写代码。
Yeah?
是啊
AUDIENCE: How are the vertices comparable?
听众：顶点的可比性如何？
In what way?
用什么方式？
PROFESSOR: Oh, so that's a good question.
教授：哦，这是一个好问题。
And I should have made that clearer.
我应该更清楚地说明这一点。
So, Q is a priority queue.
因此，Q是优先级队列。
And the priorities of the vertices are the d values, OK?
顶点的优先级是d值，好吗？
s being null is clear, I hope.
我希望可以将null清除。
That's clear.
很清楚
And then Q being the set of vertices are clear, as well.
然后，作为顶点集合的Q也很清楚。
Now, Q is a priority queue, OK?
现在，Q是一个优先队列，好吗？
And we'll talk about how we'll implement this priority
我们将讨论如何实现此优先级
queue, and the complexity of Dijkstra,
排队以及Dijkstra的复杂性，
before we're done here.
在这里完成之前。
But, as an ADT, as an Abstract Data Type,
但是，作为ADT，作为抽象数据类型，
think of Q as being a priority queue.
认为Q是优先队列。
And there's priorities associated
还有优先事项
with each vertex that's in Q. And these priorities change.
Q中的每个顶点。这些优先级会改变。
And they're the d values.
它们是d值。
All right?
好吧？
So the priorities.
因此优先考虑。
So, initially, d of s-- small s-- is 0.
因此，最初，s的d（小s）为0。
And all of the other ones are infinity.
其他所有的都是无限的。
So it's clear that, the very first time, you're
很明显，第一次，你是
going to set u to be small s, which is a starting vertex.
设置u为小s，这是一个起始顶点。
And then you relax the edges coming out of s,
然后放松从s出来的边缘，
potentially change some of these other infinity values
可能会更改其他一些无穷大值
of the vertices that you can reach
您可以达到的顶点数
from s to be less than infinity.
从s小于无穷大。
And you're going to, essentially,
从本质上讲，您将要
change the values of the priority queue.
更改优先级队列的值。
And go around.
快走吧
And then select the min value the next time.
然后下次选择最小值。
And so on and so forth.
等等等等。
OK?
好？
Thanks for the question.
谢谢你的问题。
Any other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
OK.
好。
So, let's just go through a couple of steps in an example.
因此，在一个示例中，我们仅需完成几个步骤。
I'm not going to go through the whole thing.
我不会经历整个事情。
But you'll see an execution of Dijkstra in the nodes.
但是您会在节点中看到Dijkstra的执行。
I think it's worth spending just a couple of minutes going
我认为值得花几分钟的时间
through the first few steps of a Dijkstra execution.
完成Dijkstra执行的前几个步骤。
Just so how this priority queue works is clear,
正因为如此，此优先级队列的工作方式很清楚，
let's take a look at a directed graph that has five vertices.
让我们看一下有五个顶点的有向图。
So that's 7.
那就是7。
So let's start with a being the starting vertex.
因此，让我们从成为起始顶点开始。
And so d of a is 0.
因此a的d为0。
And d of b through e are all infinity.
b到e的d都是无穷大。
Your s is null to begin with.
您的s为null。
And Q has all of the five vertices in it.
Q中包含所有五个顶点。
So extract-min is going to select a.
因此，extract-min将选择a。
That's the only one that is a 0.
那是唯一一个为0的数字。
Because you've got 0, infinity, infinity, infinity, infinity.
因为您有0，所以无穷大，无穷大，无穷大，无穷大。
And so, you select that, and you set s to be a.
因此，您选择了它，并将s设置为a。
And once you set s to be a, you relax
一旦将设置为a，就可以放松
the edges coming out of a.
边缘出来
And there's two of them.
有两个。
So you end up with 0, 10, 3, infinity, infinity.
因此，您最终得到0、10、3，无穷大，无穷大。
And the next extract-min is going to select 3.
下一个提取分钟数将选择3。
And you're going to set s to be a comma c.
并且您将s设置为逗号c。
And so you're, essentially, doing
因此，从本质上讲，您正在做
kind of a breadth-first search.
一种广度优先的搜索。
But you're being greedy.
但是你很贪心。
It's a mixed breadth-first depth-first search.
这是混合的广度优先深度优先的搜索。
You do a breadth-first search when
您何时进行广度优先搜索
you're given a particular vertex,
给您一个特定的顶点，
and you look at all of the vertices
然后你看所有的顶点
that you can reach from that vertex.
您可以从该顶点到达。
And then you say, I'm a greedy algorithm.
然后你说，我是一个贪婪的算法。
I'm going to pick the vertex in this frontier
我要在这个边界中选择顶点
that I've just created, that is the shortest distance
我刚创建的那是最短的距离
away from me, that has the lowest priority value.
远离我，那是最低优先级值。
And, in this case, it would be c because this other one is 10.
并且，在这种情况下，它将是c，因为另一个是10。
And this is shorter.
这更短。
Right?
对？
So that's why we pick c over here.
这就是为什么我们在这里选择c。
And one last one.
最后一个。
Once you process c, you're going to end up
处理c之后，您将结束
processing this edge going out here.
处理这个边缘在这里。
This edge going out there.
这个边缘在那里。
This edge going out this way.
这种优势以这种方式出现。
And you're going to end up with 0, 7, 3, 11, 5.
您将得到0、7、3、11、5。
And you've processed a bunch of edges coming out of c.
并且您已经处理了c产生的许多边缘。
And, at this point, 0 is gone and 3 is gone.
并且，此时，0消失了，3消失了。
I'm just writing the values here,
我只是在这里写值
just so you know what they are.
以便您知道它们是什么。
But these are out of the picture because, in s, those values
但是这些都不在图片中，因为在s中，这些值
should never change.
不应该改变。
Dijkstra essentially guarantees.
Dijkstra本质上保证。
And that's the proof of correctness
这就是正确性的证明
that takes a bit of doing, is that this value is never
需要花点时间做的是，这个值永远不会
going to reduce anymore.
会减少。
The pre-value is never going to reduce.
预值永远不会减少。
And it's been put into s.
它已放入s。
But what's remaining now is 5.
但是现在剩下的是5。
And that corresponds to the e vertex.
并且对应于e顶点。
So s becomes a, c, e.
所以s变成a，c，e。
The 5 gets stuck in there.
5个卡在那里。
And so on and so forth.
等等等等。
All right?
好吧？
So, that's Dijkstra.
那就是Dijkstra。
And now, let's start complexity.
现在，让我们开始复杂性。
So, it we have the code for Dijkstra on the left,
因此，左侧有Dijkstra的代码，
we have an ADT associated with the priority queue.
我们有一个与优先级队列关联的ADT。
And now, we're back to talking like we
现在，我们回到像我们这样说话
did early on in the term, where we compared linked lists,
在学期初期比较链接列表，
and arrays, and heaps, and trees.
和数组，堆和树。
And said, for a particular set of operations,
并说，对于一组特定的操作，
which one is going to be the best?
哪一个最好？
OK?
好？
So, if you analyze Dijkstra, and you look at the pseudocode
因此，如果您分析Dijkstra，然后查看伪代码
first, and you say, what are the operations that I'm performing?
首先，您说我正在执行什么操作？
I got an operation here, corresponding to theta v
我在这里做了一个操作，对应于theta v
inserts into the priority queue.
插入优先级队列。
And that's inserting things into Q.
这就是在Q中插入东西。
I got theta v extract-min operations.
我得到了theta v extract-min操作。
I'm only going to delete a vertex once, process of vertex
我只会删除一次顶点，顶点的过程
once.
一旦。
And that's why I have theta v extract operations.
这就是为什么我要进行theta v提取操作。
And I have theta e, what decrease key or update
我有说什么，减少键或更新
key operations because when I do, I relax here.
关键操作，因为当我这样做时，我会在这里放松。
I'm decreasing the key.
我正在减少钥匙。
It's in particular, it's not an update key.
特别是，它不是更新密钥。
It happens to be a decrease key, which is not a big deal.
它恰好是一个减少键，这没什么大不了的。
We don't need to get into that.
我们不需要介入。
But you are reducing the d value.
但是您正在降低d值。
So it's a decrease key operation.
因此，这是一个减少键的操作。
And, again, it's theta e because, in a directed graph,
再说一次，这是因为在有向图中
you're only going to process each edge that's
您只需要处理
coming out of the vertex once.
从顶点出来一次。
Since you're processing each vertex once,
由于您一次处理每个顶点，
and you're looking at all of the outgoing edges
而且您正在查看所有向外的边缘
from that vertex.
从那个顶点。
OK?
好？
So that's what you can get looking at the pseudocode.
这就是您可以查看伪代码的地方。
And now, you're a data structure designer.
现在，您是数据结构设计师。
And you have some choices here, with respect
尊敬的您在这里有一些选择
to actually implementing the priority queue.
实际实现优先级队列。
And let's look at the complexity of Dijkstra for arrays.
让我们看一下Dijkstra数组的复杂性。
So, suppose I ended up using an array
所以，假设我最终使用了一个数组
structure for the priority queue.
优先级队列的结构。
But then, what do I have?
但是，那我有什么呢？
I have, if I look at this, my extract-min, what
如果我看这个的话，我的提取物最小
is the complexity of extract-min in an array?
数组中extract-min的复杂性是什么？
AUDIENCE: Theta v.
听众：Theta v。
PROFESSOR: Theta v. And what's the complexity
教授：Theta v。复杂性是什么
of a decrease key in an array?
数组中的减少键？
I just go access that element.
我只是去访问那个元素。
And I change it.
我改变了。
State of one, right?
状态一，对不对？
So I have theta v for extract-min.
所以我有theta v提取分钟。
I'll just call it ex-min.
我就叫它ex-min。
Theta one for decrease key.
减小键的Theta一。
And if I go do the multiplication,
如果我去做乘法，
I get theta v times v plus e times 1, or a constant,
我得到theta v乘以v加e乘以1或一个常数，
which is theta v squared.
是θv的平方。
Because I know that e is order v squared.
因为我知道e是v的平方。
Right?
对？
If I have a simple graph, it may be a complete graph,
如果我有一个简单的图，它可能是一个完整的图，
but-- we talked about this last time.
但是-我们上一次谈到了这一点。
e is, at most, v squared.
e最多为v的平方。
So I can just call this theta v squared.
所以我可以称这个θv平方。
All right?
好吧？
So we have a theta v squared Dijkstra implementation
所以我们有一个theta v平方的Dijkstra实现
that uses an array structure.
使用数组结构。
But do we want to use an array structure?
但是我们是否要使用数组结构？
What data structure should we use?
我们应该使用什么数据结构？
Yeah?
是啊
AUDIENCE: Heap.
听众：堆。
PROFESSOR: You can use it a min-heap.
教授：您可以使用它的最小堆。
Exactly right.
非常正确。
So, if you use a binary min-heap,
因此，如果您使用二进制最小堆，
then my extract-min is finding the min is a constant
那么我的min-min就发现min是一个常数
because you just pick it up from the top.
因为您只是从顶部拾起它。
But we know that, if you want to update the heap,
但是我们知道，如果您要更新堆，
and delete it, then it's going to take that theta log v.
并删除它，那么它将使用theta log v。
And decrease key is the same thing.
和减少键是同一回事。
Theta log v. So that's worse than array.
Theta log v。因此，这比数组还糟。
And if I go do the multiplication again,
如果我再去做乘法，
I get v log v plus e log v. OK?
我得到v log v加e log v。好吗？
And this is not quite the complexity that I put up,
这并不是我所说的复杂性，
as some of you may remember, last time.
你们中有些人可能记得，上次
This is not the optimum complexity of Dijkstra.
这不是Dijkstra的最佳复杂性。
Or an optimal complexity of Dijkstra.
或Dijkstra的最佳复杂度。
You can actually take this out by using a data structure that
实际上，您可以使用一个
we won't talk about in 006.
我们不会在006中谈论。
But you can read about it.
但是您可以阅读。
It's not 6006 level material.
这不是6006级材料。
You're not responsible for this in 006.
您在006中对此不承担任何责任。
But it's got a Fibonacci heap.
但是有斐波那契堆。
And you might learn about it in 6046.
您可能会在6046年了解它。
The Fibonacci heap is an amortized data structure
Fibonacci堆是分期摊销的数据结构
that has theta log v for extract-min.
的theta log v为extract-min。
And theta one amortized time for decrease key.
并为减少密钥分摊一次时间。
And what's nice about it is that,
这样做的好处是，
once you do that, you end up with theta v log v plus e time.
一旦这样做，您最终将获得theta v log v加上e时间。
And that's the complexity I put up way back, I guess,
我想这就是我提出的复杂性，
last Thursday.
上周四。
So that's to show you, with respect to two special cases,
因此，这是针对两个特殊情况向您展示，
we have the DAGs, which are linear time, essentially.
我们有DAG，基本上是线性时间。
And Dijkstra, with amortized, and their proper data
还有Dijkstra（摊销后的费用）及其适当的数据
structure, also, essentially, linear time.
结构，基本上也是线性时间。
Right?
对？
Next time, we'll look at the general case
下次，我们将看一般情况
where we have potentially negative cycles.
我们有潜在的负周期。
And we end up with algorithms that have greater complexity.
最后，我们得出了具有更高复杂性的算法。
See you next time.
下次见。